Guide to the Hyde Park, Kenwood, and Woodlawn Neighborhoods Collection 1883-2004
University of Chicago Library
Hyde Park, Kenwood, and Woodlawn Neighborhoods. Collection
5.25 linear feet (7 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The Hyde Park-Kenwood and Woodlawn Records contain articles, journals, small publications, brochures, correspondence, neighborhood directories, flyers, newsletters, advertisements, neighborhood guides, pamphlets, proposals, reports, and newspapers concerning the history of Hyde Park and its surrounding neighborhoods, as well as the urban renewal movement.
Information on Use
Access
This collection is open for research.
Historical Note
Before European settlement, the Chicago area functioned as a trade center for various Native American nations, such as the Potawatomi, Myaamia (Miami), and Illiniwek Confederacy nations. Other nations that lived in this region were the Ottawa, Sauk, Ojibwe, Kiikaapoi (Kickapoo), Mascouten, Wea, Delaware, Winnebago, Menominee, and Mesquakie (Fox) nations. The first non-native settler in Chicago was Jean Baptiste Point du Sable, a Haitian from the French colony of Saint-Domingue, who by 1790 had established a trading settlement near the Chicago River. After several wars and raids between Myaamia and Iroquois nations, in the late 18th century the Ojibwe and Potawatomi nations took control over the Chicago area. It was ultimately the Potawatomi nation that, with the Treaty of Chicago in 1833, ceded their remaining lands in Illinois, Wisconsin, and Michigan to the American government.
Twenty years later, Paul Cornell, a lawyer, real estate spectator, and cousin of the founder of Cornell University, purchased 300 acres of land between 51st and 55th street. Cornell had envisioned creating a residential neighborhood for Chicago businessmen and their families and quickly Hyde Park became that suburban retreat. In 1861, Hyde Park was incorporated as an independent township, called Hyde Park Township, and its boundaries were extended south from 39th to 63rd Streets to 138th Street and west to State Street.
Woodlawn, previous a part of the Hyde Park Township, is a neighborhood south of Hyde Park extending north to 60th Street, south to 67 Street, and west to King Drive. The first non-native settlers of Woodlawn were Dutch farmers who arrived in the 1850s. These farmers were able to sell their produce to merchants via the Illinois Central Railroad, which in 1862 opened a station on 63rd Street.
Kenwood, also a former Hyde Park Township neighborhood, was settled in the 1850s by Chicago individuals who sought a respite from the city. The first of these residents was Dr. John A. Kennicott, who built a home near the Illinois Central Railroad tracks at 48th Street. Dr. Kennicott named his home Kenwood after his ancestral land in Scotland, and eventually the name Kenwood came to be applied to the land between 43rd Street and 51st Street, and west to Cottage Grove Avenue.
In 1889, Hyde Park Township, including the neighborhoods of Kenwood and Woodlawn, was annexed to the city of Chicago.
Though the University of Chicago was originally was located in the Bronzeville neighborhood, on the northwest corner of 35th Street and Cottage Grove Avenue, through the efforts of the American Baptist Education Society and billionaire John D. Rockefeller, the university was moved to Hyde Park in 1890
In 1893, The World’s Columbian Exposition was hosted in Hyde Park-Kenwood and Woodlawn, which, alongside an influx of residents, brought increased attention and development to the neighborhoods. During this period, Hyde Park was an affluent white neighborhood governed by racially segregating covenants that prevented African Americans from purchasing or occupying property.
In the 1950s, Both Hyde Park-Kenwood and Woodlawn experienced racial tensions and declining housing conditions, which led to a “white flight” as middle class white families left the area. In response to deteriorating housing conditions and economic decline, during the 1950s and 1960s the University of Chicago sponsored an urban renewal plan. This plan involved demolishing and redeveloping entire blocks of buildings in disrepair. Significantly, substandard housing primarily populated by low-income African Americans was demolished and replaced, but these former residents could not afford to live in these newly developed areas. The goal of this renewal plan was to create an affluent but diverse community, and after this plan, the average income of Hyde Park increased sharply by 70 percent, but the population of African Americans decreased by 40 percent.
Scope Note
This collection is organized into 3 series:
Series I: History
Series II: Urban Renewal Movement
Series III: Oversized
The Hyde Park-Kenwood and Woodlawn Records contain articles, journals, small publications, brochures, correspondence, neighborhood directories, flyers, newsletters, advertisements, neighborhood guides, pamphlets, proposals, reports, and newspapers concerning the history of Hyde Park and its surrounding neighborhoods, as well as the urban renewal movement.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
Browse finding aids by topic.
Hyde Park Historical Society. Collection
Hyde Park-Kenwood Razed Buildings. Collection
Hyde Park-Kenwood Community Conference. Records
University of Chicago. Center for Urban Studies. Records
University of Chicago. University Extension. Records
University of Chicago. Woodlawn Social Services Center. Records
Subject Headings
Community development -- Illinois -- Chicago; Urban renewal -- Illinois -- Chicago; Hyde Park (Chicago, Ill.); Kenwood (Chicago, Ill.); Woodlawn (Chicago, Ill.)
INVENTORY
- Series I: History
  This series contains newspaper and journal articles, small publications, newsletters, correspondence, brochures, directories, and miscellaneous flyers and pamphlets. The materials date from 1883 to 2004 and are arranged by type and then chronologically.
  - Subseries 1: Hyde Park
    - Articles, 1956-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Publications, 1929-1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Commemorations and Fairs, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Hyde Park Golden Jubilee, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Hyde Park Historical Society, 1979-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hyde Park Historical Society, 1984-1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Joseph Regenstein Library, 1972-1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - University Brochures, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - University Correspondence and Invitations, 1998-2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1883-1992 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 2: Woodlawn
    - Articles and Publications, 1941-1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - The Book of Woodlawn, 1920-1930 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - The Coliseum, 1897-1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Jackson Park, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous, 1917-1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Subseries 3: Southside and Chicago
    - Articles and Publications, 1926-1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Chicago’s Great South Shore, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 4: Directories
    - Neighborhood Classified Phone Directory, 1959-1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Neighborhood Phone Directory, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Neighborhood Phone Directory, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Neighborhood Phone Directory, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Neighborhood Phone Directory 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Neighborhood Phone Directory, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Neighborhood Directory, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Neighborhood Yellow Pages, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Hyde Park Chamber of Commerce Directory, 1986-1996 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1964-1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 5: Hyde Park Businesses
    - Publications and Newsletters, 1979-2005 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Flyers and Advertisements, 1979-2007 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 6: Publications
    - Articles, 1959-1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Journals and Magazines, 1979-1989 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - The Hyde Park Jacket, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Housing Guides, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Hyde Park Guides, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - University Guides to Chicago, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Brochures and Pamphlets, 1987-2002 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Series II: Urban Renewal
  This series contains press releases, newspaper and journal articles, brochures and pamphlets, reports, proposals, and personal correspondence related to the urban redevelopment movement led by the University in Hyde Park, Kenwood, and Woodlawn neighborhoods. The materials date from 1953 to 2002 and are arranged by type, and then chronologically.
  - Subseries 1: University of Chicago Campus Development and Neighborhood Housing
    - University City, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - The Neighborhood Program, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - South Campus, 1960-1963 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - The Faculty Committee on Rental Policies, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - The Hyde Park Kenwood Renewal Years, 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - South East Chicago Commission, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - The Chicago Public Housing Controversy, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - University Publications, 1953-1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - University Reports, 1956-1969 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Press Releases, 1959-1962 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2: Community Development
    - The Hyde Park Kenwood Community Conference, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - The Factual Background of the “Hyde Park-Kenwood Story”, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Harper Court, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Rebuilding Ghetto Communities for the People Who Live There, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Saul Alinsky and the Industrial Areas Foundation, 1962-1965 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - The Woodlawn Organization (TWO), 1964-1969 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - ‘Crisis in Black and White’ Reviews, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Articles, 1960-1993 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Journals, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Brochures and Flyers, 1965-1995 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 3: Religious Organizing
    - Articles, 1963-1965 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - The Christian Century, 1963-1965 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 4: Reports and Proposals
    - Commercial Club of Chicago Report, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Community Appraisal Study, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - South East Chicago Renewal Project, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Webb and Knapp Proposals, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - City Council Proposed Ordinance, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - People and Neighborhood Renewal Report, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Proposal for the Long-term Needs of Woodlawn, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Secondary Education Park Proposals, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Community Improvement and Redevelopment, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Jackson Park Case Study, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Alternatives for Planning Kenwood Oakland, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Report to Chicago Plan Commission, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Woodlawn Service Program Final Report, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - University-Community Partnerships: Current Practices vol. 2, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Hyde Park Residents Focus Groups and Survey, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Series III: Oversized
  This series contains press releases, newspaper clippings, newspaper issues, magazine issues, and journal issues. The materials date from 1923 to 2004 and are arranged by type and then chronologically.
  - Subseries 1: Press Releases
    - The Hyde Park Story, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 2: Newspapers and Journals
    - Miscellaneous Newspaper and Journal Clippings, 1923-1983 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Chicago Daily News Clippings, 1957-1962 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Chicago Sun-Times Clippings, 1957-1961 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - The Woodlawn Observer vol. 4 no. 8, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Holiday Magazine, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Chicago Magazine, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Hyde Park-Kenwood Voices vol. 2 no. 8, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - The Chicago Journal vol. 6 no. 12, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Lake Shore Perspectives vol. 1 no. 1, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Hyde Park Citizen vol. 5 no. 12, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - The Resource Fall 1995 no.7, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - The Chronicle of Higher Education, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 3: Hyde Park Herald
    - The Hyde Park Herald vol. 75 no. 44, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - The Hyde Park Herald vol. 76 no. 18, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - The Hyde Park Herald vol. 31 no. 15, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - The Hyde Park Herald vol. 31 no. 16, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - The Hyde Park Herald vol. 124 no. 29, 2004 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - The Hyde Park Herald vol. 75 no. 34, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Subseries 4: University of Chicago Newspapers
    - The Chicago Maroon vol. 85 no. 4, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - The Chicago Maroon vol. 86 no. 9, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - The Chicago Maroon vol. 87 no. 39, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - The Chicago Maroon vol. 88 no. 33, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Free Press Student Newspaper vol. 2 no. 6, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Subseries 5: Chicago Tribune
    - Chicago Tribune, Jul 23 1960 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Chicago Tribune, May 29 1985 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Chicago Tribune, Sep 29 1985 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Chicago Tribune, May 20 1987 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Chicago Tribune, May 8 1991 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1938-1967 (Box 8, Folder 30)